Some people are partial to tea. Some
people are partial to coffee. But which
is better for you across all causes of
mortality, cardiovascular health, even
respiratory diseases and digestive
diseases? The answer will stir up some
controversy steeped in
datadriven mystery as we brew a
delicious Yeah, I gotta be honest with
you. I'm lost. I was trying to stick to,
you know, a few different brewing
analogies together that I sort of lost
the plot. So, let's just move on. In
this uh study, which involved almost
500,000 participants, quantified the
amount of coffee and tea that people
consume and tracked over 15 years and
collected the amount of deaths or
disease prevalence across that time.
They then compared the disease or death
prevalence in each drink condition, so
coffee or tea as well as the amount of
consumption. So we'll go over the
amounts too. Now the idea behind looking
at these drinks is because they share
several factors between them, but they
also have distinct compounds within them
that may give one or the other an edge.
Like uh Robo Wars where one robot gets a
flamethrower strapped to it and the
other has a hefty hammer. except they're
duking it out in your artery. Well,
let's again move let's move on. The
reality is coffee and tea share
compounds like caffeine and chlorogenic
acid. I have such trouble saying that.
Clorogenic acid is known to act as an
antioxidant cell but also stimulates the
production of antioxidants inside your
cells. It also inhibits inflammation
reducing interlucan 6 and tumor necrosis
factor alpha levels. But tea contains
compounds like other flavonoids which
stimulate molecules like nitric oxide
which lead to the opening of our
arteries that drops blood pressure. On
the other hand, coffee has molecules
like melanoidins.
Melanoidins another difficult one that
okay melanoidins which can be taken up
by microbes in our gut and produce
beneficial fats that interact with our
organs and also reduce inflammatory
molecule production. These uh same
molecules also reduce the activity of
other pro-inflammatory molecules like
cycllo oxygenases. So much we need to
get into there, but the big point here
is that while they share beneficial
molecules, they also have distinct
molecules in certain respects. Which
raises this question of will the hammer
win or will the flamethrower? Let's look
at the data. Round one, all cause
mortality fight.
Coffee is up top and tea is on the
bottom. The dotted line is on both
graphs indicates the neutral risk as in
no added or reduced risk compared to
people who don't consume coffee or tea.
If the shaded lines fall below the
dotted 1.0 line that's reduced risk and
if it goes above that's increased risk.
The further right the shaded lines that
indicates greater consumption of the
respective drink. So clearly one to two
cups of either drink is linked to the
greatest reduction in risk.
Fascinatingly though, greater coffee
consumption above four cups per day
seems to be linked to no benefit or
increased risk. And yet we don't see
that when looking at tea consumption. By
the way, the tea is a mixed sample of
green tea and black tea consumers. So
based on these data, tea seems superior,
but does that maintain when looking at
specific disease states? Round two,
cardiovascular disease. Fight.
In regard to cardiovascular disease,
again, we see a somewhat similar
situation. Again, we see an initial
benefit of coffee that goes away with
greater consumption. Although, something
similar happens with tea. We don't see
that similarity until 10 or so cups of
tea, which is pretty high. I'll spare
you the Mortal Kombat fight entrance and
mention that we see here that this is
also mostly the case when looking at
respiratory and digestive diseases.
These are defined as flu and pneumonia
as well as bronchitis, emphyma, asthma
and COPD for the respiratory and
esophageal stomach and intestinal
disorders, colitis and even liver
conditions like cerosis among others for
the digestive diseases. Strangely, even
higher doses of C coffee seem to track
with significant benefit in digestive
diseases. But again that nod seems to be
toward tea consumption. So why do we see
this loss of risk reduction otherwise
stated an increase in risk when we get
to greater coffee consumption? And
what's the optimal amount of each? Then
also what happens when you combine tea
and coffee? Do you mutate into a
superhuman with a troubled past? And
what about uh if you're younger than 60
or if you're not overweight or if you
already consume a healthy diet. Are
these results still apparent? Aside from
the first two questions, which we'll get
into shortly, there's a lot of
additional questions that I'll be going
over in the extended version of this
analysis that you're watching, which is
included with the Physionic Insiders
along with, do I say it? live sessions
with yours truly, a private community,
an insider podcast that pulls together
all the most important information into
one place, written research reviews, and
shortened summaries. I mean, need I go
on. Anyway, the link to join is uh down
below for the insiders in the
description box. Hope to see you there.
Anyway, as uh many will know who've been
along the physionic journey, we've been
discussing a correlation. So an
association between something like all
cause
dwit all cause death risk and coffee
consumption. But the researchers did a
series of other adjustments as well.
I'll list them on the screen. That means
that it probably wasn't something like
smoking that actually caused this
effect. But it can't be ruled out that
there's some other factor that's not
listed here that could muddy the
results. I can think of one that I don't
see here that has been accounted for in
other analyses on coffee. In previous
analyses on coffee, researchers also
accounted for sleep, but it's absent
here. Now, consider if you consume six
coffees per day, what impact that will
have on your sleep. And since sleep is
intimately related to cardiovascular
health along with many other types of
health, it seems reasonable that could
be a major confounding factor. Of
course, we don't know that for a fact,
but it's plausible, especially since
caffeine content in tea is lower than in
coffee. The researchers even mentioned
that the population here uh may be
different than those included in other
studies. For example, some studies use
uh nurses populations, which means now
you're talking about a group of people
with a particular behavior or
responsibilities that may not extend to
the rest of the population outside the
medical field. That is, there may also
be methodological differences between
studies. Okay. But let's assume that
everything here is above board. What's
the optimal dose according to this
analysis? Well, in general, because
we're talking about the entire sample,
not a subsample, and because there are
multiple outcomes, death, cardiovascular
disease, and so on, the coffee benefits
top out around 1 to two cups per day. On
the other hand, the tea consumption is
closer to three cups per day. Again, not
distinguishing between green and black
tea. In the end, I still think there are
some outstanding questions, but the
overall message here is that tea may
offer more consistent positive effects
than coffee. Probably because it was
equipped with that hammer instead of the
flamethrower. Although coffee is still
linked to better health as well, up to a
point. The amount linked to best
outcomes, if that's all cause mortality
or otherwise, is either one to two cups
of coffee or about three cups of tea,
green or black. But you know that coffee
consumption may be more beneficial if
timed correctly, which may be another
reason we don't see benefits at higher
doses. And I cover coffee timing and
more in this next video. And if you
drink tea, I haven't forgotten you. I
cover more right here. See you over
there.